Finding Aid for the William Edward Naylor papers, 1961-1986 LSC.2326
UCLA Library Special Collections
William Edward Naylor papers
1961-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
Naylor, William Edward, 1943-
LSC.2326
4.4 linear feet (11 boxes)
The collection contains the research files of William Edward Naylor dating from 1969 to 1986 which document his work at the Network Measurement Center, as well as the development of the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET). It includes computer science and network publications and articles; notes and calculations by Naylor; and printed programs and datasets.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
William Edward Naylor; Gift; 2013.
Custodial History
This collection was acquired by University Archivist Charlotte Brown in 2013 for a proposed Kleinrock Center for Internet Studies (KCIS) at UCLA. The former collection number was KCIS005.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9981331723606533
Biography/History
William Edward Naylor was a PhD student and researcher with the UCLA Computer Science Department from 1969 to 1978. Working with Leonard Kleinrock, Naylor conducted numerous measurement experiments on the ARPANET, determining its traffic patterns as well as areas for improvement. He also worked on packet voice, an early form of Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP), the Atlantic Packet Satellite Network (SATNET), and the Packet Radio Network (PRNET).
Scope and Content
This collection documents the research of William Edward Naylor who was a student and researcher at the UCLA Computer Science Department. He was responsible for measuring and testing packet routing within the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) from the late 1960s to the mid-1980s. The records in this collection document Naylor's research during the development of ARPANET, a project initiated by the Department of Defense. The collection includes notes, mathematical calculations, presentation slides, technical reports, monthly reports, memoranda, publications, booklets, programs and data on continuous form paper, articles, course notes and textbooks, and correspondence. The materials contain data and research on a variety of internet-related and computer science topics including queueing theory, the Poisson process, Contention-based Priority Oriented Demand Assignment (CPODA), flow control, packet routing, block traffic, network simulations, network designs, and saturated cuts algorithms.
Organization and Arrangement
The following arrangement was imposed on the collection:
Series 1: Research files, 1969-1986
Series 2: Fortran guides, 1961-1986
Series 3: Publications and booklets, 1975-1981
Related Material
Leonard Kleinrock papers. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Michael Allen Wingfield papers. Available at Library Special Collections, University Archives, UCLA.
Computer Science Department. Student papers, abstracts, and reports. 1965-1977. Available at Library Special Collections, University Archives, UCLA.
ARPANET (Computer network).; United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency; Naylor, William Edward, 1943- -- Archives
- Research files, 1969-1986
  - Binder B (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Binder C (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Binder 02 Theory of Queues (Box 1, Folder 5-6, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Binder 03 Appendix I and II (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Binder 04 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Binder 05 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Binder 01 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Xerox 1700/1710 Test (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kahn Packet Trace (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - IMP Storage Util Bob Chen's stuff (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - IMP Sys (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - BBN Quarterlies (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NMC packet data reports (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - ARPANET Stat Pack data values (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - ARPANET Monthly Summary 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ARPANET Monthly Summary 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Network Descriptions (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - ISI Talk ARPANET delay & Rtg (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Processing Delay / Switch Capacity (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - RT Delay Histo (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Norway to Hawaii (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - DCA (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 76 DCA Experiment (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CPODA Model Notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Monthly Reports (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Measured Results CPODA (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CPODA Block Traffic Measurement, Simulation, and Analysis (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - C-PODA Results (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - CPODA Model (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - SATNET (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sabnet Overhead (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Satelite distances (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - F-TDMA, R-TDMA, and S-ALOHA Measurements in SATNET (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speech Related Papers (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NAC Report (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Milsatcom (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - NMG Note 13 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Real-time Transmission in a Packet Switched Network NMG Note 15 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - UCLA Mtg stuff (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Queueing Theory (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Random Access Methods (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Poisson Arrival Process Statistics (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Packet Network Articles (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Packet Routing (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Routing (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Queuing Analysis of a Buffered Urn Scheme (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Multiserver Load Sharing (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - m server delay dynamic vs static assignment M/M/m, m(E2/M/1), m(M/M/I) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - M/M/I/K (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - M/M/m Arrival Stats (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - M/M/m/K blocking prob (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Measurement and Performance Papers (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Protocols (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Block Traffic Notes (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Error Control (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Test plan results (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - CRC Computation (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Network Working Group Comments (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Data Transfer and Trace Experiments Results (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Flow Control (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Analysis (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Network Simulations (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Reliability (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Network Design (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Saturated Cuts Algorithms (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Tariffs (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Programming Data (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Tracing Data (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - CPT's (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - To Be Filed (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
- Fortran guides, 1961-1986
  - Fortran IV Programming and Applications, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Guides on Fortran, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1966, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
- Publications and booklets, 1975-1981
  - Communications ACM, 1976 January (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - History of the ARPANET: The First Decade, 1981 April (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Stream Traffic Communication in Packet Switched Networks, 1977 August (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - C-PODA Block Traffic Measurement, Simulation and Analysis, 1978 November (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - On the Spatial Capacity of Packet Radio Networks, 1980 May (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Switching and Flow Control Techniques in Computer Communications Networks, 1978 February (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Flow Control in Store-And-Forward Computer Networks, 1981 April (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Unifications and Extensions of the Multiple Access Communications Problem, 1981 July (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Broadcast Protocols in Packet Switched Computer Networks, 1977 April (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Activities in Computers and Communications (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Adaptive Routing Algorithms for Distributed Computer Networks, 1974 May (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Xerox Corporation Petition for Rule Making, 1978 November (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Interprocess Communication Protocols for Computer Networks, 1975 December (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - IEEE Communications Society 1979 Membership Directory (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - ARPANET Directory, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 6-8)